Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/li-helena-tao (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

SAP Successfactors
Salary Benchmarking
Salary Structures

Languages

Chinese (Native or Bilingual) English (Native or Bilingual)

Certifications

Global Remuneration Professional (GRP)

Global Professional in Human Resources (GPHR)

Senior Professional in Human Resources (SPHR)

Li (Helena) Tao

People Analytics | Compensation & Benefits | Data Science Steuben County, New York, United States

Summary

20+ years of HR experience with Cornell MILR degree equipped me with deep expertise in compensation & benefits, M&A, HR analytics, and talent management. This domain expertise, coupled with data science skills from MIT education, constitutes a unique combination of capabilities and gives me an edge to solve complex business problems from the lens of workforce intelligence, with analytical mindset and data science techniques.

Well-rounded HR leader with diverse leadership experiences in compensation & benefits, HR generalist capacity and people analytics, who delivers strategic business impact with analytics rigor.

Experience

Corning Incorporated 11 years 4 months

HR Director, People Analytics February 2018 - Present (5 years 3 months)

Corning, New York, United States

- 1. Set up People Analytics strategy and roadmap.
- 2. Led a global HR team to identify the key metrics to address shared challenges across businesses and functions, and built an automated Global HR Analytics Dashboard to enable business success. Led change management efforts to advance the journey of data - insight - actions - impact.
- 3. Led employee attrition analysis, used machine learning to identify hot spots and drive actions, used logistic regression and econometrics to measure the effect of new hires attrition, used regression to evaluate whether "great resignation" was a pandemic-driven phenomenon
- 4. Led HR Data Privacy, a member of Global Data Privacy Council.
- Led the implementation and change management of SAP SuccessFactors Workforce Analytics and Report-Story tools to accelerate Data Democratization.

Human Resources Manager, Global Research & International Labs
Page 1 of 3

December 2014 - February 2018 (3 years 3 months)
Corning, NY

HR leader for Global Research organization, with business presence in US (New York and California), France, Russia, China, Taiwan and India, supporting SVP of Global Research.

Led the Global Organization Network Analysis Project to improve innovation effectiveness: identify SMEs for core competencies, discover silos, assess talent, locate key network roles (energizers, brokers).

Compensation and Benefits Manager - Americas Region, Global Compensation and Benefits
January 2012 - December 2014 (3 years)
Corning, NY

Leader of Compensation and Benefits Center of Excellence for the Americas region, covering US, Canada, Mexico and Brazil. Expertise in M&A due diligence and integration, benefits harmonization, compensation and benefits analytics.

Corning Incorporated 7 years 7 months

HR Manager - Corporate Research February 2008 - August 2010 (2 years 7 months) Corning, NY

Independently conducted an analytics project to answer CTO's question of how to improve productivity for scientists and technicians. Worked with CTO, Chief of Staff, and 70 directors, manager, scientists and technicians, and collected internal and external qualitative and quantitative data. The analytics provided insights to CTO and his staff on key dimensions affecting scientist productivity, offered recommendations on how to manage scientists and technicians for enhanced productivity, and verified CTO's hypothesis of scientist/technician ratio for future staffing model.

HR Manager - Corning International Greater China October 2005 - February 2008 (2 years 5 months) Shanghai, China

HR leader for Corning International Greater China region.

Compensation & Benefits Manager - Corning Greater China Region January 2004 - October 2005 (1 year 10 months) Shanghai, China

Leader of Compensation & Benefits Center of Excellence in Greater China region, providing consulting services to both business and HR leaders in areas of reward and recognition.

HR Manager

February 2003 - December 2003 (11 months)

Shanghai, China

HR leader of Corning Frequency Control Shanghai, a wholly owned manufacturing site of Corning Frequency Control business.

Philips

Compensation & Benefits Manager/HR Manager-OPU January 2000 - January 2003 (3 years 1 month)

Shanghai, China

Leader of Compensation and Benefits function for Philips Optical Storage Shanghai, including Audio-Video plant and Optical Pick-up Unit Plant, up to 3,000 employees with a mix of professional and operational capacities.

HR leader of Philips Optical Pick-up Unit (OPU) Plant, supported OPU plant in rapid ramp-up phase (new plant startup up to 1,500 employees) and led organization restructuring project to ensure smooth plant closure.

Education

MIT Professional Education

Applied Data Science Program · (May 2022 - August 2022)

MITx on edX

Fundamentals of Statistics · (May 2021 - September 2021)

MITx on edX

Introduction to Computer Science and Programming Using Python · (January 2021 - March 2021)

MITx on edX

Data Analysis in Social Science · (June 2020 - September 2020)

MITx on edX

Probability - The Science of Uncertainty and Data · (January 2020 - May 2020)